Speaker 1: they're not doing it just because they're dumb they're doing it because they're scared this is really a panic move on the part of the government it's a hail mary to try to stop long-term interest rates from rising by announcing that the government is going to buy the bonds that everybody else is selling remember they're basically stepping in front of this trade because the market doesn't want treasuries the market is selling treasuries and now the u.s government has decided that it's going to use
Speaker 1: taxpayer money, basically, to buy the treasuries that everybody else is selling. Clearly, it's not a smart financial move, so why are they doing it? They are trying to slow down the rate of increase in long-term bonds. But the trade-off is they're shortening the average maturity on the national debt, which is already just under six years, and it's going to get a lot shorter as this program expands because it's not going to be enough.
Speaker 1: This is just the opening bit. This is not the end of it. This is more like the beginning.
Well, this is going to
Speaker 3: be another one of those I told you so podcasts because what happened today, well, I told
Speaker 4: you so. I've been talking on the podcast for a while now about the relentless rise in
the
Speaker 4: in long-term bond yields in the United States. In fact, between this podcast and the one that I did a few days ago, we made new highs in yields going back over 19 years. The yield on the 30-year U.S. Treasury got above 5.3. I think I saw it top out around 5.32 and the yield on the 10-year
Speaker 4: was about 4.7 to 4.73. Now yesterday there was a bit of buying in the bond market. So the yields moved up slightly from their lows as the stock market went down a bit. And it looked like to me that there might have been a little bit of rotation going on.
Speaker 4: where investors were selling some equities to buy bonds. And I expect that rotation will continue as bond yields continue to rise. Today's rally in bonds notwithstanding. But the bombshell that was dropped
Speaker 1: on the markets today, that is what I've been forecasting. Because I knew that the government wasn't going to sit by
Speaker 1: and let rates rise now of course that's exactly what they should do but they're not going to do it because i know how problematic rising bond yields is going to be not only for the u.s government because it has to finance so much debt and by the way today the national debt topped
Speaker 4: 40 trillion and the announcement by the treasury today which i'll get to and that 40 trillion dollar national debt
Speaker 4: that's not a coincidence that's why it's happening and by the way about 30 percent of that national debt has been added while trump has been president trump has now presided over the biggest increase in the national debt of any president the record holder right now or was barack obama he was president for
Speaker 1: eight years but trump has already topped him
and
Speaker 1: he still has about two and a half years left to go now it's possible in his second term he will actually
Speaker 4: break biden's record because biden holds the record for the most debt added in a single term trump has added 11.58 trillion so far during his first term and a half ish but biden has this single term record trump may break it uh during
Speaker 4: his, uh, his second term. You know, it's laughable because if you go back to the 2016 campaign, when the national debt was about 19 trillion and Donald Trump said he was going to pay it all off and he thought it might take him eight years to reduce the national debt to zero, zero. And you know, when he was asked, are you going to raise taxes to eliminate the national debt? He said, I don't have to, I'm just going to negotiate great trade deals. He said, it's all about
Speaker 1: the deal.
Speaker 1: It's all about our lousy trade deals. And somehow, if we negotiated better deals, we could pay off the entire debt. Instead, the debt has doubled since 2016, and much of that on Trump's watch. Now, I know a lot of people, you know, want to say, hey, it's not Trump's fault, right? Congress has the purse strings. Congress is passing these budgets, which is true, but he doesn't have to sign them. He could veto all of these budgets,
Speaker 1: and make Congress override his veto. In fact, he didn't have to sign off on the increases in the debt limit.
He
Speaker 5 (higher-pitched voice): could have vetoed all of those. So you can't say it's not Trump's fault because it's Congress. He worked with Congress. In fact, in many cases, he was pounding the table for the big deficits that Congress passed.
Speaker 5 (higher-pitched voice): So it wasn't like he was pushing against them and saying, "Come on, Congress, stop spending all this money. You got to cut spending." No, he was encouraging Congress to spend recklessly. And in fact, when Elon Musk came to town early in his second term, supposedly to cut spending with Doge, Trump ran him out of town. So Trump is very much responsible for these deficits. You know, if I were president, I would have vetoed every one of those budgets.
Speaker 5 (higher-pitched voice): I would have made sure that if they were going to increase the debt, it was going to be over my veto. They were going to have to have two thirds votes in both houses to overcome my veto. But this is a big day, 40 trillion in debt. It'll be 50 trillion before you know it. In fact, it may even be 50 trillion.
Speaker 5 (higher-pitched voice): before Trump finishes his term and that would be a monumental feat of disaster not something that you'd want to brag about or you know be proud of but I think it's possible that it could actually happen but the news that came out today which again is what I'm expecting and it's at odds with the message being sent from the Fed because we got the FOMC minutes
Speaker 5 (higher-pitched voice): today as well. I'm going to get to that too. But before we got those minutes, because the minutes came out at 2 p.m. Eastern and this news announcement came out at 8:30 in the morning. Now, of course, I'm sure that Trump's buddies,
Speaker 5 (higher-pitched voice): knew that this was coming, right? They probably front ran this announcement because Trump didn't just, you know, come up with it. Now, of course, it was the Treasury Department that announced it, but, you know, that's part of the Trump administration. So I'm sure that they traded off this information yesterday, probably, and got positioned because they announced the policy before the bell rang, about 8.30, right?
Speaker 5 (higher-pitched voice): Eastern time and what the Treasury announced was that they were now going to be doubling their buyback of long-term Treasuries. These are Treasury bonds, you know, 20, 30-year maturities. They were buying $2 billion every time they bought and now they're going to buy $4 billion Treasuries they're going to buy. And as soon as the announcement came out, the price of gold spiked. In fact, I didn't even know the announcement. I had to look it up. I saw gold moving.
Speaker 5 (higher-pitched voice): saw bitcoin moving i saw stock futures moving and i had to look up the news i wasn't even sure because remember i'm here out on vacation and so i had i had to you know just go online and try to figure out what was going on but you know a lot of people
Speaker 5 (higher-pitched voice): We're calling this QE or QE Lite. This is not QE. The Fed did not announce anything. This is the Treasury. The Treasury is going to be buying more long-term bonds. But unlike the Fed, the Treasury doesn't have the printing press and can't just create money out of thin air to buy long-term bonds. So where does it get the money? It sells more short-term bonds. So it's financing the debt.
Speaker 5 (higher-pitched voice): It's buying back the previously issued longer term debt and replacing it with shorter term debt. Now, why are they doing this? Because this is a very reckless thing to do. First of all, if you look at the
Speaker 4: average coupon on the debt right now, the longer duration debt, the debt that's going out from 10 years or longer,
Speaker 1: the average coupon is 3.44%. Why would you want to refinance that? 30-year rates now we're at 5.3. Now, they moved down just below 5.2. I think I looked, it was 5.18. And the 10-year is down at, you know, 4.6 something. But if you've got all this long-term debt locked up at 3.44, why the hell would you want to refinance that?
Speaker 1: with treasury bills at four percent.
Speaker 4: I mean, that'd be like somebody having a trade mortgage. Maybe they got, you know, 25 years left on it. And you got a three and a half percent mortgage. Why
Speaker 1: the hell would you want to pay that off by borrowing more money and getting a one year arm? Nobody would be dumb enough
Speaker 4: to do that except our government. Now, they're not doing it just because they're
Speaker 1: dumb. They're doing it because they're scared. This is really a panic move.
on
Speaker 1: the part of the government. It's a hail Mary to try to stop long-term interest rates from rising by announcing that the government is going to buy the bonds that everybody else is selling. Remember, they're basically stepping in front of this trade because the market doesn't want treasuries. The market is selling treasuries and now the U.S. government has decided
Speaker 1: that it's going to use taxpayer money, basically, to buy the treasuries that everybody else is selling. Clearly, it's not a smart financial move. So why are they doing it? They are trying to slow down the rate of increase in long-term bonds. But the trade-off is they're shortening the average maturity on the national debt.
Speaker 1: which is already just under six years. And it's going to get a lot shorter as this program expands because it's not going to be enough. This is just the opening bid, right? This is not the end of it. This is more like the beginning. And I've been saying this for a while, that the Treasury was going to up their buybacks. But this also is going to make it much harder for the Fed
to
Speaker 1: raise short-term because now the government itself is more vulnerable to the increase because it's having to refinance this short-term debt. So why would they do that? Why would the government
Speaker 5 (higher-pitched voice): trade in long-term debt that they've already locked in these low yields to expose itself to all of this risk and it's all expedience? They're kicking the can down the road. They're trying to trade some relief from the short-term pain for long-term pain.
but
Speaker 5 (higher-pitched voice): the long-term pain is going to come when all this short-term debt matures and it has to be rolled over or because the fed is cognizant of that vulnerability it doesn't raise interest rates in fact when people are calling this again quantitative easing it's not because the fed is not doing the buying so the money supply isn't expanding as a result of this but it will
Speaker 1: Because as the U.S. government is selling these short-term treasuries, who's going to buy those? I think the Fed is going to end up buying them by actually launching a QE program. And in fact, because the Treasury is not going to be buying enough long-term bonds to stop the rise, they'll slow it down a bit, but it's not going to stop it, the Fed is ultimately going to come join the party.
Speaker 1: So, QE is coming. In fact, the Fed is already doing QE. It's just not an official program, but they are going to have to ramp it up. And clearly, they're not going to be able to hike rates. It would put monetary policy at odds with fiscal policy. The fiscal
Speaker 4: policy is stimulative. They're trying to lower long-term rates. So basically, the government running big deficits and buying treasuries is going
to
Speaker 4: running an accommodative, highly
Speaker 1: accommodative fiscal policy, which is complicating the Fed's job of trying to run a tight money policy because the Fed is worried about inflation being too high. Well, now the Treasury is making the Fed's job harder by putting even more upward pressure on inflation. So as soon as, you know, the news is out and people are talking about, you know, whether it's QE or it's more like Operation Twist. That was, if you remember that, And that happened.
Speaker 1: happened after they did QE, the first QE. I think it was between QE2 and QE3, they did Operation Twist. And if you remember at the time, I was calling it Operation Screw because they were screwing over the country because the Fed was selling short-term debt to buy long-term debt to move long-term interest rates down because the markets were more sensitive to long-term rates and the mortgage market was more sensitive. So this is like an Operation Twist
Speaker 1: Only it's the U.S. Treasurer that's doing it, not the Fed. But again, this is just a peek at what is going to happen. The government is already panicking. They're going to trade inflation to try to slow down interest rates. Again, I said, I agree with Kevin Warsh, inflation is a choice. He acted as if the Fed won't choose inflation. I said from the beginning, of course it's gonna choose inflation because it can't choose the opposite.
Speaker 1: And the fact that the Treasury is already moving in
Speaker 6: this direction is pretty clear that the Fed is going to be moving in the same direction.
Speaker 7: Losing weight can feel a lot like the stock market. You're up one month, down the next. And if you don't understand what's actually driving the moves, you end up reacting instead of planning. Most people treat weight loss the same way they treat trading, chasing the short-term result with no strategy for what comes after. Noom takes a different approach. It's a health and wellness app that combines GLP-1 medication with behavioral support. The medication.
Speaker 7: medication kickstarts the weight loss, and the app builds the habits that make it stick. Daily lessons, food logging, help managing food noise, and staying consistent when life gets busy. Their own analysis found people lost 37% more weight with Noom than with a GLP-1 alone. That's the point. The meds are a tool, not a magic solution. The habits are the asset. They call it lose for keeps, and that's the right framing. You're not renting a result. You're building one you actually own. Progress that holds up even if you eventually stop the medication. The Noom GLP-1
Speaker 7: program starts at $39 and is delivered to your door in as little as seven days. Start your GLP-1 journey today at Noom.com. That's N-O-O-M.com. Noom. Lose for keeps. Initial one-month subscription from $39 plus tax and $99 plus tax per month thereafter. Costs of medication not included. Final pricing depends upon program selection. Results based on a January 2026 analysis of 14,203 Noom GLP-1.
Speaker 7: Rx program members who logged weight over a 40-week period. Higher app engagement was associated with greater weight loss at 16
Speaker 4: weeks. Before I forget, I want to remind everybody that you got one month, if you want to join me in Panama City for the Schiff Sovereign Plan B
Speaker 4: conference. And it's going to be a hell of an event. And I'm really looking forward to being back in Panama City. You know, I was there earlier in the year and I really enjoyed being there. And that's one of the reasons that we're having this conference there. I wanted to come back so you guys could join. You got to go to the website. It's shiftsovereign.com and get some information on the Plan B event in Panama City. Sign up and I will see you there.
in
Speaker 4: about a month. Anyway, I want to get back to the Fed because later in the day after we got this surprise announcement,
Speaker 1: of course, I don't know why anybody is surprised. I mean, I wasn't surprised. I mean, I've been waiting for this. I mean, I know the box that the government is in. They just can't allow rates to rise. And so they're doing whatever they can to push back against the free market. But the free market wants higher interest rates for a reason. And the reason is we have too much He's dead.
Speaker 1: And the way you stop too much debt is by making it more expensive to borrow. What the government wants to do is prevent that so they can keep borrowing more. But all that does is make the eventual crisis that much worse because the bubble gets much bigger than it would have had the market popped it sooner. In fact, popped it a
Speaker 4: long time ago if it wasn't for government
Speaker 4: intervention into the market. But anyway, when the FOMC minutes were announced at two o'clock, they were actually more hawkish than the markets had expected. And had it not been for the morning announcement, the stock market might have tanked
Speaker 1: today. The bond market might have gone down. Yields might have gone up.
Speaker 1: because nobody wanted to cut rates. Everybody was talking about hiking rates. You had, of course, you had the dissenters who wanted to hike rates right away. But the opinion of the FOMC was that inflation is a problem. It's too high and it's more likely to go up. Now, you know, they were looking for excuses or who they blame the inflation on. Some of them were blaming it on AI. The stock market doesn't cause inflation.
Speaker 1: AI doesn't cause inflation. The Federal Reserve causes inflation. The government helps the Federal Reserve create inflation by running these big deficits. So the fact that we've got a $40 trillion national debt and that it's rising sharply, because when I did my podcast a few days ago, we were still about $80 billion away or $100 billion, but we moved up quickly. And this is what's causing inflation. And again, it's not the war that's causing inflation. It's the way we
pick
Speaker 1: pay for the war. It's the deficits that we're running. We didn't raise
Speaker 5 (higher-pitched voice): taxes to pay for the war. We didn't cut other spending to free up resources for the war. We just spent. And so bigger deficits mean more inflation. But the Fed never talks about it. They never talk about these big deficits as a cause of inflation. They never talk about all the money supply and the money they're printing, although they are talking about the balance sheet and they're talking about a need to shrink the a balance sheet, well, how are they going to do that when the Fed is doing
Speaker 5 (higher-pitched voice): Operation Twist? What, they're going to try to sell back the bonds that the U.S. government is buying? They're not going to be negating what Treasury is doing. Obviously, they're going to coordinate. They're going to work together. So there's no way. But had it not been for this announcement, this could have been a big problem for the markets. In fact, I don't know, maybe the Treasury knew
Speaker 5 (higher-pitched voice): that these FOMC minutes were going to be hawkish. And they had to take the sting out of it before it had a chance to affect the market. So the markets basically shrugged it off. The odds of a rate hike went down, even though the FOMC minutes were more hawkish than expected because of the action of the U.S. Treasury. Now, the market confirms
Speaker 5 (higher-pitched voice): my interpretation, because look at what happened to the price of gold. So yesterday, gold dropped about 80 bucks, closed near the lows of the day. That was probably the worst day gold's had in at least a month, if not more. And silver was down. Today, gold rallied about $185, closed above $4,500.
Speaker 1: In fact, last night, gold was down about 20 bucks.
Speaker 1: So it had a $200 intraday rally. Huge. And a reversal day, technically, because today we took out yesterday's low in gold and then closed way above yesterday's
Speaker 4: high. So technical reversal, we're now about 13% above the low for gold. Gold bottomed out just below $4,000. If you remember, I was pounding the table on this podcast saying, look,
$4,000,
Speaker 4: uh that's the low you gotta you know you gotta buy that and you know here we are now above 4500 silver had a big day as well it closed above 66 dollars an ounce let me see where it is right now i'm recording this at night it's about 9 30 at night and well silver is actually down about 18 cents now 66 71 so yeah well above 66 in fact i think earlier tonight it might have gotten above 67 Gold's retreating it's down about
Speaker 4: $20, but it's still trading above $4,500. So a very significant day for gold and silver. The mining stocks were on fire today. A lot of these stocks were up 7%, 8%,
Speaker 1: 9%, 10%, 11%, 12%. I think the GDX, GDXJ, 8%. You know, both of those indexes in the last month,
Speaker 1: are up close to 40%. And they're up for the exact reason I said they were going to be up. Gold went down. Gold stocks went down because people were fooled by the Kevin Warsh show, by, you know, the whole, you know, dog and pony. Oh, yeah, we're going to be tough on inflation. It's just going back down to 2%. Like everybody was talking, oh, he's this new sheriff in town. He's Paul Volcker reincarnate. And I was saying, no way. The markets are wrong. He's not.
Speaker 1: going to do this. It's all talk. And I kept saying, look at what the Fed is doing. Don't pay attention to what Warsh is saying. Look at money supply. Look at the balance sheet. Look at the fact that they're not hiking. All of the tough talk didn't jive with the fact that they were sitting on their hands and doing nothing. And now the Treasury is making it even harder.
for
Speaker 1: the Fed to fight inflation. In fact, they're putting a lot more pressure to create inflation because as the Treasury continues to shorten the maturity of the national debt, whenever the Fed raises interest rates, it inflicts that much more
Speaker 5 (higher-pitched voice): damage on the budget. The budget deficit goes up because now it costs more to service
Speaker 1: that debt.
Speaker 1: And so as the Fed tries to fight inflation, it actually sows the seeds for more inflation because now these bigger deficits, how the government going to finance them? The Fed's going to ultimately have to finance them. That's why I kept saying the fall in the bond market, people were worried about rising bond yields being bearish for gold and silver. And I kept saying they're not, they're bullish because the rising bond yields
are
Speaker 1: are going to force QE the rising bond yields are going to weaken the economy they're going to cause bigger budget deficits and in fact the reason that bond yields were rising was because of inflation and it wasn't that higher bond yields were going to be some kind of competition for gold like oh i better sell my gold so i can get five percent on a 10-year treasury
Speaker 1: No, it was just another reason
Speaker 5 (higher-pitched voice): to sell your treasuries because treasury prices are falling. When yields are rising on treasuries, that means the price of treasuries is going down. That means if you own treasuries,
Speaker 1: you are losing. So what do you want to do? You want to get rid of your treasuries and you want to buy gold.
Speaker 5 (higher-pitched voice): So a weak bond market is bullish for gold.
Speaker 5 (higher-pitched voice): It's not bearish. And for the exact reasons that we saw today, because the bond market was so weak, that is forcing the Treasury to actually buy those bonds. And that's going to force the Federal Reserve to do the exact same thing. Now, interestingly enough,
Speaker 5 (higher-pitched voice): We didn't get a big stock market rally today. I mean, the market rallied, but it wasn't much. It was about even 200 points. Let me see how much the Dow was up. I think it was a couple hundred points. The Nasdaq was barely positive. In fact, there were quite a few tech stocks that actually went down.
the
Speaker 5 (higher-pitched voice): news and you know even though the bond market rallied it wasn't that significant of a rally another market that was affected was the US dollar the dollar index got whacked about 80 basis points we're now back below 99 98 85 and the weakness of the dollar helped pushed oil prices up
Speaker 5 (higher-pitched voice): over 2%, back above $86 a barrel and rising. So now you have a break between oil and bond yields because they had been trading together. Bond yields up, oil up, bond yields down, oil down. But today the bond market shrugged off the rise in oil prices because of the Treasury announcement. But it's not going to shrug it off for long. In
fact,
Speaker 5 (higher-pitched voice): Because the Treasury, it is weakening and the weakness of the dollar is going to be pushing up bond yields and inflation, right? As oil prices and other commodity prices are rising, that's going to further complicate the Fed's job. Because now the Fed is going to have to not hike in an environment where there's even more upward pressure on consumer prices. That is a direct result.
Speaker 5 (higher-pitched voice): of the weakness of the dollar. And obviously, Treasury had to know that this announcement was going to weaken the dollar and complicate the Fed's problem when it comes to inflation because a stronger dollar helps restrain consumer prices. It helps keep a lid on import prices. But when you have a policy that is weakening the dollar, that is putting more upward pressure
on
Speaker 5 (higher-pitched voice): oil and commodity prices make it even more difficult for the Fed not to hike rates. But of course, it's not going to hike rates, especially with Treasury doing this operation twist, which obviously is going to expand because the markets now know this. Bond prices are going to keep falling. This is just a temporary balance.
the
Speaker 5 (higher-pitched voice): markets are going to test the Treasury's resolve and ultimately the Fed's resolve. And again, a lot of this too is because of what's happening in Japan, right? The weakness of the dollar now is taking some of the pressure off the Japanese yen and therefore some of the pressure off Japan to sell U.S. Treasuries. But, you know, if you think about this, why the hell would the Treasury be doing this in an environment where long-term yields,
Speaker 5 (higher-pitched voice): are rising the last thing you'd want to do is pay off long-term debt and borrow more short-term debt and you know 20 years ago when rates were this high and i know i hear some people saying hey it's no big deal that rates are up here because rates were here 20 years ago and everything was fine well first of all everything wasn't fine but you can't compare
Speaker 5 (higher-pitched voice): the environment today to the environment 20 years ago when the national debt was less than a quarter of its present size. So you're talking about 5% of a huge number, not a small number. But it's also, it's not just that, it's the trajectory of rates. 20 years ago, we were still in a major bond bull market and yields were
in a
Speaker 5 (higher-pitched voice): long-term decline. Now it's the opposite. Yields are rising. This is a bear market in
Speaker 5 (higher-pitched voice): bonds. And we're only about five or six years into it. So rates are going to keep rising. They're not going to fall like they're going to rise and they're going to be a lot higher.
Speaker 7: The economy lost 23,000 jobs in July. And on top of that, the government went back and erased another 103,000 jobs from May and June that it now admits were never created. But here's what's interesting. I pulled this story up on ground news where 311 different outlets covered it. And you can read every headline side by side. The Associated Press ran
Speaker 7: And with, quote, U.S. job markets stalled in July, delivering political setback to Trump. The New York Post ran the same numbers as, quote, interest rate hikes could be put on hold. Same report, same government data. One outlet decided this was a story about Trump. The other decided it was good news for the stock market. Neither one is lying to you. They're just choosing what you focus on. And if you only read one of them, that choice was made for you.
Speaker 7: That's why I love Ground News. It's an app and a website that pulls every story together in one place so you can compare exactly how each outlet frames it. And you can see who owns each one because ownership shapes the narrative. On this story, Fox Business, The New York Post, and Investors Business Daily all carry the same tag, Murdoch Family. Three outlets, one owner right there on the screen. I've built my whole career on looking past the headline number to the actual data. Ground News lets you do that with the news itself. So go to groundnews.com.
Speaker 7: Now, it wasn't just gold and
Speaker 4: silver that rallied in response to the Treasurer's announcement. Bitcoin also went along
for the rocket
Speaker 4: In fact, it got off to a slower start and it was trailing gold and silver. But then it just took off and Bitcoin actually got above 70,000. We had been trading at around 62,000, 63,000, I think it was 63,000 when I did my last podcast. And as I'm recording this one, we're around 69,500. I know a lot of the Bitcoiners are getting really excited.
Speaker 4: Again, the announcement
Speaker 8: caught some people off guard. Obviously, I think maybe there were some shorts that covered. Some people got excited. They ran into Bitcoin because this is it, right? This is the big move on inflation. This is a
Speaker 4: precursor to quantitative easing. Everyone's going to get out of the dollar. They're going to buy gold and silver. They're going to buy Bitcoin. They're going to buy gold and silver, but they're not going to buy
Speaker 1: Bitcoin. I mean, people are hoping...
Speaker 1: that they buy Bitcoin, and I think this trade is built on hope. So I think the big difference between the rally in gold and silver and the rally we had in Bitcoin today is that the gold and silver
Speaker 4: rally is the real deal. Not only are gold and silver going to retain their gains, but they're going to add to them. Whereas I expect Bitcoin to reverse and go back down.
And I
Speaker 4: think tech stocks, you know, which showed a lot of weakness today in that they didn't get a rally off of this news. So if we're going to get a bigger correction in tech, then
Speaker 1: Bitcoin is going to follow tech lower. It's not going to follow gold and silver higher. But what's more important is gold and silver are leading.
Speaker 1: Gold moved a lot more. Silver moved a lot more before Bitcoin. Bitcoin didn't lead the charge, it followed behind. And so people would have thought, "Oh, it's even more
Speaker 5 (higher-pitched voice): sensitive than gold and silver." It's not, it was less sensitive than gold and silver. Now we also got some more economic news that came out today, again, that is bearish on the economy. The housing numbers, look at housing starts.
Speaker 5 (higher-pitched voice): and permits way below what had been estimated. They were looking for 1.415
Speaker 4: million. And the number came out at 1.239 million. This is one of the lowest numbers that we've had, I guess, since the COVID lockdowns.
And
Speaker 4: the same thing with pending home sales, which plunged, although they
Speaker 1: revised up last month, so it wasn't quite as bad. It was down 5.4% was the original report for June. And now they revised that to down 4.8%. But there was supposed to be a rebound of 1.4% in
Speaker 5 (higher-pitched voice): July. Instead, we had another decline of 2.3%.
Speaker 5 (higher-pitched voice): So overall, between the revision and the worst number in July, it was weaker than expected. In fact, the index, the pending home sales index, which was reported at 72.5 in June, was supposed to go up to 72.9. Instead, it went all the way down to 71.2. So this is another reason why the Treasury is in panic mode with respect to bond market, because the mortgage rates are set off the 10-year U.S.
Speaker 5 (higher-pitched voice): treasury now i don't know why they're not set off the 30-year u.s treasury that would make more sense because these are 30-year bonds so why are they pricing them off a 10-year treasury when you got 20 more years of risk and they have a 30-year treasury slot they don't have one so you would think a 30-year mortgage would relate to a 30-year treasury and i think even though they're priced off of the tens the appetite should be more consistent with the 30 because that's how much risk you're assuming you're collecting that mortgage
Speaker 5 (higher-pitched voice): for 30 years. I mean, assuming that, you know, it stays. Obviously, a lot of mortgages get repaid early. And that's probably part of the reason because it's not necessarily 30 years. But believe me, those mortgages that were taken out in the twos and the threes, you better believe those things are not going to pay off early. The owners of those, they're going to want to keep them, take them to the grave. They're going to hold them to milk them as much as they can.
Speaker 5 (higher-pitched voice): Because the mortgage is what's so valuable, more so than the property. So a lot of banks or a lot of lenders are stuck with this low yielding 30 year paper. They're hoping that like whoever borrowed that money sells the house or something so they can get out of jail on these mortgages because they're really liabilities.
for
Speaker 5 (higher-pitched voice): the lenders, they're not assets, they'd love to get rid of these things. But anyway, so we got that negative economic news. Other news that came out was on trade. Now, there were supposed to be these 50% tariffs that were going to be kicking in on Canada. And again, the tariffs are not on Canada.
Speaker 1: They're on Americans who want to buy Canadian goods, and we buy a lot of Canadian goods.
Speaker 1: Tariffs on Canadian goods are particularly problematic for Americans who are buying those goods.
Now, of
Speaker 1: course, yes, the Canadian government, right, they would just assume not have those tariffs because by making Canadian goods more expensive for Americans, Americans buy fewer Canadian goods. And that's, you know, that's a problem for the Canadian companies because they want to sell goods to America. We're their customers. But the fact that they're
Speaker 5 (higher-pitched voice): worried about the tariffs.
It's not because
Speaker 5 (higher-pitched voice): because they're worried that they're going to pay them, they're not going to pay them. They're worried that Americans are going to pay them. And because Americans have to pay the tariffs, they're not going to buy as much stuff, right? Because if Canada ate the tariffs, then Americans would keep buying their products. But that doesn't happen. That was promised. Nobody is eating our tariffs. In fact, look at the Chinese Yuan. It's higher today than it was when Trump took office. And so the whole selling point
If
Speaker 5 (higher-pitched voice): you remember all of these economic guys that were advising Trump, they said that the Chinese Yuan was going to tank. That's how they were going to eat our tariffs. It was going to be a weaker currency. So we were going to be able to buy their stuff cheaper because their currency was going to go down. And that's how they were going to pay our tariffs. Well their currency went up. And what does that mean? That means not only are we paying the tariffs on Chinese goods, but we're paying a higher exchange rate to get the Chinese Yuan.
The
Speaker 5 (higher-pitched voice): goods are more expensive, even more so than the tariffs because of the unfavorable exchange rate. But anyway, so Canada obvies these tariffs because it's not good for their businesses to not be able to sell as much stuff to Americans because...
Speaker 5 (higher-pitched voice): a lot of americans can't afford to pay the tariffs now some americans will it's not like all of the trade between the u.s and canada is going to grind to a halt the americans who can afford to pay the higher prices are going to pay the higher prices but other americans will be priced out of the market they're just out of luck and so they obviously didn't want the tariffs well donald trump today says okay i'm going to postpone they were supposed to kick in i guess today
Speaker 5 (higher-pitched voice): And he said, okay, you know, we're so close to this great deal. Again, that's exactly what Trump does every time, right? He tacos out. Oh, we're going to have these 50% tariffs. And then he says, oh, we got this great deal. But they don't have a deal. I don't know what they have, but apparently Canada, Mark Carney is out there talking about how this is such a great deal for Canada. Like we really got one over on the Americans here. We've got this great deal that we negotiated. I mean, that might sabotage it because I don't think Trump likes hearing the other side bragging
Speaker 1: about
how
Speaker 1: they got the better end of the deal. But again, this news came out, which is good news for the markets, right? Again, I mean, if the markets believed that these tariffs were
Speaker 4: coming, because the tariffs, you know, they're on a lot of raw materials that we need. And so to the extent that the tariffs are inputted, and I think tariffs were going to go from
Speaker 1: like 25% to 50%, some big number. And so, yes, it is...
a
Speaker 1: positive for the U.S. economy that we're not going to get hit with these tariffs. But the good news really didn't do much to lift the markets, considering that you also had the news coming out of Treasury. So maybe the markets are looking at this so-called good news with a high degree of skepticism, which they should, because the fact that the U.S. government is panicking,
Speaker 1: The fact that rising interest rates are so problematic or rising bond yields that the Treasury had to announce that this program, that they are going to be increasing their buyback. I think stock market investors should be concerned about this, especially since this is not going to work. $2 billion, $4 billion, that is a spit in the ocean.
Speaker 1: compared to the two $3 trillion
Speaker 5 (higher-pitched voice): annual deficits that we are running. So rates are going to go up. And the fact that the Treasury is buying these bonds, that's not going to encourage other people because other investors know this is political. The fact that the U.S. government is buying it is reason enough to want to sell it. I mean, do you
Speaker 1: think they're doing a smart investment? Do you think this is good economically? somebody was at the treasurer was looking at it and thinking, yes, this is
Speaker 5 (higher-pitched voice): a
Speaker 5 (higher-pitched voice): sound move we want to buy up all these treasuries because they're cheap no that's not why they're buying them they're buying them because they know if they don't buy them they're going to keep falling in price and the yields are going to keep rising so it's artificial so the fact that the treasury has to rescue the bond market is a pretty good sign that the bond market is in trouble and if even the u.s government knows that the treasury market is in trouble why would you want to buy
Speaker 5 (higher-pitched voice): If anything, you're going to sell to the government. You always want to fade whatever the government is doing because the government isn't doing the smart thing. The government is doing the politically
Speaker 4: expedient thing. Anyway, if the markets were surprised by what the Treasury announced today, they're going to be shocked by the stuff that's going to be happening in the months and years ahead. Listeners to my podcast are not going to be surprised by any of this because all of this is
Speaker 4: what we expect to happen. This is all, you know, basic economics. It's not rocket science. It's kind of amazing to me that people can't connect the dots here. But Fed credibility is really gonna come into question when it's being undercut by the U.S. Treasury, because
Speaker 1: this new policy is clearly
Speaker 1: and easing of conditions. A movement to artificially suppress otherwise rising long-term interest rates, right? Those rising long-term interest rates would have cooled the economy, right? They would have dampened economic activity. But now, because the Fed is trying to artificially suppress them, that is a stimulus.
Speaker 1: Yet the Fed is supposedly trying to fight inflation with a more restrictive monetary policy. Well, that's just been undercut. And again, as I said earlier, it's going to put tremendous pressure, both behind the scenes and in front of the scenes, on the Fed to cooperate and play ball. Because how is the Fed now going to tighten policy
Speaker 1: when the Treasury is going in the opposite direction. These guys are working together. Bessett and Warsh. I mean, two Trump picks, right? Trump just picked this secretary of the Treasury. He just picked this Fed chair, right? They're his buddies. They're on his team. They're all on Team Trump.
Speaker 1: They're not going to be working at odds with one another. Unfortunately, they're going to be working hand in glove. And so we're going to see much more weakness in the U.S. dollar relative to foreign currencies than what we've already seen today. We're going to see a lot more strength in precious metals. You know, by the way, the yield on the 10-year Japanese government bond yesterday was above 4%. I mean, it's never been above 4% in its history. it's back
Speaker 1: below now at three spot nine eight. It's got a little bit of a reprieve because of the strength of the yen. But, you know, the yen is not that strong. It's not out of the woods. Let me see where the yen is trading right now. I think it's still around 159 to the
Speaker 4: U.S. dollar, even with the help it got today. 158 and a half.
Speaker 4: So it's, you know, it's strengthened a little bit, but it's
Speaker 1: still very close to the danger zone. They're going to press the Bank of Japan, just like they're now going to press the U.S. Treasury on these Treasury buybacks. $4 billion, okay, well, can you double it again to $8 billion? They're going to have to do something. And again, the Fed is going to have to come in and do the heavy lifting. Not that they're going to have to. They shouldn't.
Speaker 1: But they will because
Speaker 5 (higher-pitched voice): they have a much bigger arsenal. Remember, when they were doing QE, what was it, 40 billion, 45 billion a month? I forget, 50, 80 billion? I mean, they were buying some serious bonds when they were doing full-blown QE. Well, they actually have to do it more now because we have a much bigger debt problem than we had after the 2008 financial crisis.
The
Speaker 5 (higher-pitched voice): national debt was, what, in 2008, 2009, it was $8 or $9 trillion. And they ended up blowing up the balance sheet to $4 trillion, which was about half the size of where the national debt started. Well, half the current national debt is $20 trillion. $20 trillion QE program. That's what's coming because, you know, it's like any kind of drug habit. The more drugs you take, right, the bigger your addiction, the more drugs you need to stay high.
Speaker 5 (higher-pitched voice): $4 billion in QE would be nothing. We're a much bigger debt addict
Speaker 1: now. I mean, we're not even going to get any kind of high off of $4 trillion in QE, right? We're going to need a much bigger fix, and it's coming. And the markets haven't even begun to digest
Speaker 1: what's going to be happening. So in the meantime, look, if you miss the opportunity to buy
Speaker 5 (higher-pitched voice): $4,000 gold, well, $4,500, it's still $1,000 off the highs. Remember, gold got up to $5,500 in February. So it's still $1,000 off sale. You should take advantage of it. Silver also, below $67, silver got above $120. Maybe it was like $125. That wasn't the high.
Speaker 5 (higher-pitched voice): Right. It's just the next benchmark that it's going to take out. So it's pretty clear. I mean, it should have been clear before, but now the markets are getting it. Investors are getting it. You're seeing in the markets exactly what I've been saying. And you're seeing the government react the way I said it would react. And the Fed is doing exactly what I said it was going to do. It's
talking
Speaker 5 (higher-pitched voice): Talking tough, but acting weak, right? They speak loudly because they have no stick. And even if they had a stick, Treasury just broke it. So you need to act and you need to act fast. Hey, by the way, I know people were asking in the comments to see a little bit more of my boat. And so I
Speaker 1: put up a drone video that we took. I actually, I wasn't even on the boat. One of the crew took it with her drone, but I posted it
Speaker 4: on X so you can see the boat
in
Speaker 4: the harbor there and I you know I I'm not there anymore so I'll let you know where I was I was at Martha's Vineyard and the boat was moored right between Martha's Vineyard and Chappie Chappaquiddick and if you're old enough like me you remember what made Chappaquiddick famous was Teddy Kennedy ended
Speaker 1: up driving his car off a bridge and the girl that he was driving ended up drowning
Speaker 1: and that was a big scandal that followed teddy kennedy for his entire life and he was never able to get out from under that i mean he may have been able to run for president but for that whole a chappaquiddick incident but that that's where we were at the time that i did that podcast and in fact i was anchored you know right off the town
Speaker 1: where they filmed the movie Jaws and in fact there's still you there's a little movie theater there and they're playing Jaws like it's it plays a couple of times a week uh at this theater I guess that's uh that's part of the claim to fame but we're not there anymore and also you know people were asking about the boat you know I mentioned that we need to use the generators when we're under power because the the engines take a lot of power and so you can operate them on batteries
But
Speaker 1: they'll drain the batteries pretty fast, especially if you're going faster. If you go really slow, the batteries will last a lot longer. So we generally have to turn the generators on when the boat is moving. But when the boat's moored or at anchor like we are right now, we're just sitting here in another location. We're no longer in Martha's Vineyard, but we're at anchor. And when we're at anchor, it's quiet as can be. We don't have to turn on the generators because the batteries could power all of the systems on the boat.
Speaker 1: while it's not moving. And if we get a lot of sunshine, the sun will recharge the batteries. And so we can keep running the air conditioners, the lights, the water maker, you know, all of the hotel type functions of the boat, they can be run exclusively off batteries. It's only when we're really moving and we need more power because the engines, you know, consume a lot of power. That's when we have to deal with the noise of the generator. But even then, it's not We're allowed to, you know, I turned the generator
off
Speaker 1: a lot. And we're able to travel in silence where I just hear the waves in the ocean. You know, you can hear there's a boat coming by. It's just like a big foghorn just went off or something like that. And I can see there's a big light shining on me. But anyway, so that's it for
Speaker 4: today's podcast. Not sure what time of day this thing is going to be uploaded onto Shift Radio and onto YouTube. But whenever it is, you guys will be able to check it out. And again, I'm still going to be
Speaker 4: at sea for another couple of weeks i'm not going to be back in puerto rico till the first week of september and so uh and then i'm going to go i'll be doing my regular podcasts from my studio in puerto rico oh don't forget subscribe to this youtube channel and don't forget to
Speaker 1: follow me now on x i'm almost at 1.7
Speaker 1: million followers. So my follower count has really been moving up along with the viewers. A lot more people are listening to my podcast now. A lot more people are following me, which is a good thing because the information that I'm giving out is very important. And not only do I want you to take it in, but you need to share it with your friends because the more people that understand what's going on and that understand that the problems are caused by government, not the free market, they'll understand that the solutions won't come from government. The solutions must also come from the free market. Take care, everybody.